When running an app, one may want to write
information to a file to have that information
ready to use later within the app or the next
time the app is run.
An example related to gaming can involve saving
a player’s status or collection of items
used to play games.
In our ongoing file example, we will examine
the code that writes to a file.
We also want to see what happens if we try
to write to a file that does not exist and
what happens when attempting to write to a
file that does exist.
To help demonstrate these situations, I have
my code editor, Visual Studio Code, and Explorer
side by side.
I have the 314-write file open and the folder
containing the files we will write to in this
video.
First, let’s look over this code.
On line one, we have an open method to open
a file called 314-message.txt.
The w indicates to open the file in write
mode.
Like r for reading a file, w+ will open a
file for reading and writing.
In looking at the file list in Explorer for
this folder, we do not see a file named 314-message.txt.
In running this code, then, one of two things
will happen: either the file will be created,
or we will get a message indicating that the
file does not exist.
Lines 2 and 3 write statements to the file
referred to on line 1.
Write statements write text to a file.
Then, line 4 closes the file to free up the
memory space the file occupies while it is
open.
I will run the code, and we do not get an
error message, so that is a good first step.
In our user folder, we also see the 314-message
text file appear.
One key to managing files is knowing how a
programming language will react to attempting
to write to a file that does not exist because
knowing that determines whether we need to
write code to account for a file that does
not exist.
For Python, such code is not necessary.
Let’s open the text file that’s been generated.
The write statements from lines 2 and 3 were
written to the file, but there is no line
between the two lines of code.
As we fix this problem, we will also discover
how Python handles writing to existing files.
Does the file get overwritten or appended,
meaning the text is added to an existing file?
First, we want to add an escape character,
a backslash, and an n at the end of the first
write statement on line 2.
I will place the cursor after the word configuration
and type backslash n to tell Python to add
a new line at this point.
I will then rerun the code.
Then, I will open the 314-message text file.
The text is now on two lines, and, and this
is important to know, the original file was
overwritten.
Seeing this behavior begs this question: how
do we add text to an existing file?
We will cover how in the next video.